Guide to the Colgate University Department of English records A1096
Special Collections and University Archives, Colgate University Libraries
Colgate University Department of English records
1932-1961
A1096
Special Collections and University Archives, Colgate University Libraries
6 Cubic feet
Colgate University. Department of English.
Access to Collection
Collection is open for research; however, special restrictions may apply to portions of this collection in accordance with the Colgate University Archives policy on restricted records. These restrictions may include, but are not limited to, University administrative records (closed for 30 years from date of creation), employee records (closed for 75 years), and student records (closed for 75 years in accordance with the Federal Family Education and Privacy Rights Acts (FERPA)). During the restricted period, the records will be made available to the office of origin, the staff of the University Archives, and officers of the University as necessary. Please contact Special Collections and University Archives for further information.
Annual reports.; Correspondence.; English--Study and teaching.; Financial records.; Journals (periodicals); Memorandums.; Minutes (administrative records); Syllabi.
- Various materials including courses, grades, committee minutes, and correspondence, 1932-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Papers from composition classes, 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Papers from composition classes, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Papers from composition classes, 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Schedules, diagnostic exams, class work, work sheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- The Years: 1930-44, English 272, 1957 Spring (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Stories by students in composition classes, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Stories by students in composition classes, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Colgate Writing
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 1, No. 1, 1936 December (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 1, No. 2, 1937 February (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 1, No. 3, 1937 March (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 1, No. 4, 1937 May (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 2, No. 1, 1937 December (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 2, No. 2, 1938 January (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 2, No. 2, 1938 January (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 2, No. 3, 1938 April (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 2, No. 4, 1938 May (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 3, No. 1, 1938 November (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 3, No. 2, 1939 February (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 3, No. 3, 1939 May (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 4, No. 1, 1939 December (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 4, No. 2, 1940 January (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 4, No. 3, 1940 April (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 4, No. 4, 1940 May (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 5, No. 1, 1940 December (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 5, No. 2, 1941 January (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 5, No. 3, 1941 April (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 5, No. 4, 1941 May (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 6, No. 1, 1942 January (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 6, No. 2, 1942 March (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Colgate Writing(stories from students in composition classes), Vol. 6, No. 3, 1942 April (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Faculty committees, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Educational Policy Committee minutes, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Committee on Graduate Scholarships, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Scheduling and Self Study Committee, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Educational Policy Committee minutes, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Committee on Residence Colleges, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Curriculum Sub-Committee, 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Committee on Career Guidance, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Faculty Handbook, 1954 October (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Faculty Meeting minutes, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Faculty Minutes, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Sophomore general examination, 1950 April (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Faculty news, directory, and list of new members, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1948-1952 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Comprehensive Exam, 1932-1942 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Communication about former English students, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- English concentration individual student problems, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Staff meeting minutes, 1951-1957 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Functional Writing Program, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
- The English Record, NYS English Council, 1955 Spring (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Regulations governing class attendance, 1952 September 29 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Analysis of registration, curriculum, and advising, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
- English Department travel funds, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Budget, 1952-1960 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Budget - Student employees, 1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Budget - Masque and Triangle, 1951-1960 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Comprehensive examination, 1933-1941 (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Information for advisors, concentration requirements, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Course abstract forms, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Course abstractions, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
- Mr. Berlind materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
- Mr. Daniels materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
- Mr. Hoben materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
- Exams, Mr. Kinney materials, reports, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
- Mr. Kistler materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
- Freshman test scores, 1949-1960 (Box 2, Folder 70)
- Sophomore test scores, 1953-1958 (Box 2, Folder 71)
- Schedules, 1946-1951 (Box 2, Folder 72)
- Schedules, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 73)
- Schedules, 1954-1958 (Box 2, Folder 74)
- Course catalogue and concentration information, undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
- Schedules, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 76)
- Schedules, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 77)
- Audio-visual information, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
- Handbook of Theme Analysis, Inter-college Committee on Communications Objectives, 1952 October (Box 3, Folder 79)
- Newspapers and comprehensive program information, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
- Problems in Physical Science and Chapter on English Communication for General Education in an American College, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
- Core 23 materials, 1957-1960 (Box 3, Folder 82)
- Communications, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
- Core 11 and 12 materials, undated (Box 3, Folder 84)
- English and American Language materials, undated (Box 3, Folder 85)
- Memo regarding library orders, 1959 January 8 (Box 3, Folder 86)
- Reading Lab, 1951-1955 (Box 3, Folder 87)
- Reading Lab, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 88)
- Reading Lab, 1948-1954 (Box 3, Folder 89)
- Reading lists and reading programs, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 90)
- Functional Communication Survey, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 91)
- Speech - teaching and contests, 1952-1959 (Box 3, Folder 92)
- TV and education, 1951-1958 (Box 3, Folder 93)
- TV and education, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 94)
- Writing Lab, 1951-1958 (Box 3, Folder 95)
- Writing Lab, 1951-1957 (Box 3, Folder 96)
- Orientation Writing Test, 1954, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 97)
- Evaluation of writing, 1951-1956 (Box 3, Folder 98)
- English Communication, 1948-1955 (Box 3, Folder 99)
- Eugene T. Adams materials, 1954-1960 (Box 3, Folder 100)
- Mr. F. Reed Alvord materials, 1950-1957 (Box 3, Folder 102)
- Addresses, undated (Box 3, Folder 103)
- American Association of University Professors (A.A.U.P.), undated (Box 3, Folder 104)
- American Studies, undated (Box 3, Folder 105)
- Armed Forces Information School, undated (Box 3, Folder 106)
- Correspondence (A), 1949-1956 (Box 3, Folder 107)
- Correspondence (B), 1950-1955 (Box 3, Folder 108)
- Correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 109)
- Conference on College Composition and Communication, undated (Box 3, Folder 110)
- Case materials, 1950-1956 (Box 3, Folder 111)
- College English Association, undated (Box 3, Folder 112)
- Colgate Development, undated (Box 4, Folder 113)
- Correspondence (D), 1949-1955 (Box 4, Folder 114)
- Correspondence (E), 1949-1956 (Box 4, Folder 115)
- Program materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 116)
- George Estabrooks materials, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 117)
- Dean French materials, 1944-1954 (Box 4, Folder 118)
- Ford Fund, 1955 December 15 (Box 4, Folder 119)
- Ford Fellowships, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 120)
- Scholarships, undated (Box 4, Folder 121)
- Correspondence (F), 1950-1954 (Box 4, Folder 122)
- Griffith materials, 1950-1955 (Box 4, Folder 123)
- Correspondence (G), 1949-1960 (Box 4, Folder 124)
- Correspondence (H), 1949-1955 (Box 4, Folder 125)
- Institute of International Education, 1954-1956 (Box 4, Folder 126)
- Correspondence (I), 1949-1953 (Box 4, Folder 127)
- H. Jones materials, 1950-1953 (Box 4, Folder 128)
- Correspondence (J), 1951-1954 (Box 4, Folder 129)
- Dean Kallgren materials, 1950-1956 (Box 4, Folder 130)
- Correspondence (K), 1949-1956 (Box 4, Folder 131)
- Mr. Lawson materials, 1950-1956 (Box 4, Folder 132)
- S. Lawson bibliography and other materials, 1944-1957 (Box 4, Folder 133)
- John W.S. Littlefield materials, 1949-1951 (Box 4, Folder 134)
- Correspondence (L), 1949-1953 (Box 4, Folder 135)
- Karl Lawrence materials, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 136)
- Correspondence (Mc/Mac), 1949-1955 (Box 4, Folder 137)
- Morgan materials, 1957-1960 (Box 4, Folder 138)
- Middle States Evaluation of Functional Writing Program, 1954 March 14-16 (Box 4, Folder 139)
- Rodney L. Mott materials, 1952-1956 (Box 4, Folder 140)
- Correspondence (M), 1949-1956 (Box 4, Folder 150)
- The National Council of Teachers of English, 1944-1959 (Box 4, Folder 151)
- National Citizens Commission for the Public Schools, 1950-1954 (Box 4, Folder 152)
- Correspondence (N), 1949-1956 (Box 4, Folder 153)
- New York State Council of Teachers of English, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 154)
- Correspondence (O), 1950-1955 (Box 4, Folder 155)
- Orientation materials, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 156)
- Public Relations, 1950-1956 (Box 4, Folder 157)
- Purdue English Notes, Vol. 6, No. 1, 1952 October (Box 4, Folder 158)
- Correspondence (Q), 1950 (Box 4, Folder 159)
- Registrar information, 1950-1960 (Box 4, Folder 160)
- Schedules, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 161)
- Correspondence (R), 1950-1960 (Box 4, Folder 162)
- Retirement Program, 1953 January (Box 4, Folder 163)
- State University of New York, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 164)
- State Education Department, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 165)
- Schlesser materials, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 166)
- Correspondence (S), 1949-1956 (Box 4, Folder 167)
- Correspondence (T), 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 168)
- UNESCO materials, 1953-1957 (Box 4, Folder 169)
- Correspondence (U), 1951 (Box 4, Folder 170)
- Correspondence (V), 1951-1956 (Box 4, Folder 171)
- Correspondence (W), 1949-1956 (Box 4, Folder 172)
- Mr. Waas materials, 1954-1960 (Box 4, Folder 173)
- Correspondence (Z), 1951 (Box 4, Folder 174)
- Advanced Placement materials, 1955-1959 (Box 4, Folder 175)
- Advanced Placement Essay Booklets, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 176)
- Advanced Placement materials, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 177)
- College English, 1956-1959 (Box 4, Folder 178)
- Counseling Service, undated (Box 4, Folder 179)
- Core 23: Communication, 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 180)
- College Entrance Examination Board, 1945-1960 (Box 4, Folder 181)
- Debate information, 1948-1960 (Box 4, Folder 182)
- Schedules, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 183)
- Schedules, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 184)
- Schedules, 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 185)
- Schedules, senior members, and student evaluations, 1958-1960 (Box 5, Folder 186)
- The Humanities Visiting Committee, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 187)
- Careers and areas of study in English, undated (Box 5, Folder 188)
- Program committees, undated (Box 5, Folder 189)
- Catalogue information, undated (Box 5, Folder 190)
- Concentration information, requirement, and advising, undated (Box 5, Folder 191)
- Concentration information, undated (Box 5, Folder 192)
- Memos and correspondence, 1954-1960 (Box 5, Folder 193)
- Pre-concentration forms of English concentrations, 1948, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 194)
- Honors in English, undated (Box 5, Folder 195)
- Schedule of courses spring semester, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 196)
- Fall and spring courses, 1955-56 (Box 5, Folder 197)
- Functional writing, undated (Box 5, Folder 198)
- Functional writing program, 1951-58 (Box 5, Folder 199)
- Honors candidates- English, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 200)
- Honors exam, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 201)
- Phi beta kappa certificate: Strang Lawson, 1959 June 13 (Box 5, Folder 202)
- New graduate preceptors, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 203)
- While striving man must err, undated (Box 5, Folder 204)
- Judith Gibson: "The View of Man in Representative Selections of World Literature" and "The Greek Tragic Hero", 1960 (Box 5, Folder 205)
- Human nature and statecraft in Machiavelli's de principatibus: Mary Frances Keefe, 1960 August 4 (Box 5, Folder 206)
- Our literacy and moral past from selected authors in translation- Marionlee Teitelbaum, English 545S, 1960 August 4 (Box 5, Folder 207)
- David Donahue, undated (Box 5, Folder 208)
- Harry McEntee, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 209)
- Special studies, 1960 Summer (Box 5, Folder 210)
- John Connor- English 563S, 1960 August (Box 5, Folder 211)
- Essays from English 563S, 1960 August (Box 5, Folder 212)
- Special project, English 563S- David R. McKay, 1960 August (Box 5, Folder 213)
- Summer 1960 (Box 5, Folder 214)
- English 563S, 1960 Summer (Box 5, Folder 215)
- English 545S, 1960 Summer (Box 5, Folder 216)
- Plans for teaching poetry- Gertrude Shillabeer, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 217)
- English staff meeting minutes, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 218)
- Departmental reports- Dean French, 1952-52 (Box 5, Folder 219)
- Departmental reports, 1952-53 (Box 5, Folder 220)
- Annual departmental reports, 1953-54 (Box 5, Folder 221)
- Annual departmental reports, 1954-55 (Box 5, Folder 222)
- Departmental reports, 1956-57 (Box 5, Folder 223)
- Departmental Reports, 1957-58 (Box 6, Folder 224)
- Dietrick, Richard V., 1946 (Box 6, Folder 225)
- Theodore A. Distler, president Franklin and Marshall College Lancaster, Pennsylvania, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 226)
- Directors of Divisions, 1949-50 (Box 6, Folder 227)
- Division of natural sciences, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 228)
- Dodge, Homer L., 1951 (Box 6, Folder 229)
- Miscellaneous correspondence pertaining to educational policy committee, 1955-58 (Box 6, Folder 230)
- Educational testing service, 1949-51 (Box 6, Folder 231)
- Engagement schedules- Mr. Case and Dean French, 1946-51 (Box 6, Folder 232)
- Faculty miscellaneous, 1945-53 (Box 6, Folder 233)
- Faculty evaluation forms, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 234)
- Faculty on manpower, 1944-49 (Box 6, Folder 235)
- Faculty handbook, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 236)
- Faculty requests for information, 1952-53 (Box 6, Folder 237)
- Faculty survey reports- military service and special abilities, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 238)
- Faculty tenure status, 1950-51 (Box 6, Folder 239)
- Ford foundation fellowship, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 240)
- Freedoms Foundation, Inc. Valley Forge, Pennsylvania, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 241)
- Manual education, undated (Box 6, Folder 242)
- General education workshop evaluation (Michigan State College), 1950-57 (Box 6, Folder 243)
- General education- material for NEA volume on teaching techniques in general education, 1951-52 (Box 6, Folder 244)
- Reuben Frodin, editor, The journal of general education, 1949-51 (Box 6, Folder 245)
- German students and other foreign student groups, 1950-51 (Box 6, Folder 246)
- Grimshaw, William H., 1948-50 (Box 6, Folder 247)
- Himes, Norman E., 1947-51 (Box 6, Folder 248)
- Hospital insurance, 1937-45 (Box 6, Folder 249)
- Hospitalization- Syracuse group, 1946-49 (Box 6, Folder 250)
- Hospitalization- Utica group, 1946-49 (Box 6, Folder 251)
- Institute of international education, 1947-51 (Box 6, Folder 252)
- Internships, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 253)
- F.L. Kunz- visited campus 1950 January 7- director of the foundation for integrated studies (Box 6, Folder 254)